ACTWU Sander Genis Papers 5619/037
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU Sander Genis Papers
1916-1980
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Genis, Sander
5619/037
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
6826796
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, May 17, 2010
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 25, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Biographical / Historical
Born March 4, 1895 in the Ukraine, Sander Genis was a member of the ACWA since 1915. He became the ACWA International Vice-President in 1946. He also was a member of the ACWA Minnesota Joint Board, a member of the TWUA Twin City Joint Board 1939-1946, and TWUA National Vice-President 1938 - 1946. His civic activities included the Minnesota Foreign Policy Association, Minnesota War Service Fund, War Labor Board Panel, and United Hospital Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619: ACWA Records 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio-Visual Materials 5619 C-S MB: ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files 5619 F: ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 G: ACTWU Graphics 5619 MB: ACTWU Memorabilia Collection 5619 mf: ACWA Records Parts 1-3 on Microfilm 5619 OH: ACWA Oral History Project Records 5619 P: ACTWU Photographs 5619 PUBS: ACTWU Publications 5619/001: ACTWU Collective Bargaining Agreements 5619/002: ACWA Education Department Records 5619/003: ACWA Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5619/004 fiche: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Speeches on Microfiche 5619/005: ACWA Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/006: ACTWU Executive Vice-President's Office Files 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5619/008: ACWA Rieve-Pollock Foundation Files 5619/009: ACTWU Operations Department Sidney Hillman Awards Files 5619/010: ACWA Jacob Potofsky files 5619/011: ACTWU Southern Regional Joint Board Files 5619/012: ACTWU Company Files 5619/013: ACTWU Research Department Correspondence Chronological Files 5619/014: ACWA Local 169 Files
Textile industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Genis, Sander; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Textile Workers Union of America; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization)
6826796
- Army War College, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- H. H. Broach. A Short Simple Course in Speaking, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: A Short Simple Course in Speaking, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    By H. H. Broach. Item is in English.
- ERA. Electronic Reactions of Abrams, 1922; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: ERA. Electronic Reactions of Abrams, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Alexander Marky; Upton Sinclair; Francis A. Cave; James Barr; Burton W. Swazye; Frederick Finch Strong. Reprinted from Pearson's Magazine. Item is in English.
- Sander Genis. The Menace of Nazism and Fascism, 1935; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  3 copies.
  - Item 1: The Menace of Nazism and Fascism, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By Sander Genis. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: The Menace of Nazism and Fascism, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By Sander Genis. Copy 2. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: The Menace of Nazism and Fascism, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By Sander Genis. Copy 3. Item is in English.
- Sander Genis. Notebook., Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Looseleaf. Handwritten.
- Labor Pamphlets., 1943; Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Labor in Australia: The Story of a Successful Labor Movement., Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By Lloyd Ross. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Post-War Manpower and Its Capacity To Produce., Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By S. Morris Livingston. April 1943. Reprint: Survey of Current Business. Item is in English.
- The Labor Party of Chicago and Cook County., Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Resolutions, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By The Labor Party of Chicago and Cook County. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Statement of Position, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 3: Provisional Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Laundry Workers Joint Board., 1947; Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes 4 photographs.
  - Item 1: 10th Anniversary, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Laundry Workers Joint Board. Item is in English.
- H. L. Loucks. The Great Conspiracy of the House of Morgan Exposed and How to Defeat It., 1916; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: The Great Conspiracy of the House of Morgan Exposed and How to Defeat It., Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By H. L. Loucks. Item is in English.
- Minnesota. Revised Labor Laws., 1929; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: Minnesota. Revised Labor Laws., Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    By Industrial Commission of Minnesota. Item is in English.
- Pamphlets., 1941-1943; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: Defense: One Year, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By Office of Emergency Management. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: The Philosophy of History and Its Bearing On the War, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By carl F. Taeusch. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: How To Use Bread in Modern Meals, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By Zinsmaster Baking Company. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: The "Farm Bloc" and When Do We Eat?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By ACWA (Amalagamated Clothing Workers of America). Keeping Up With Public Opinion: Amalgamated Discussion Pamphlet Series no.7 (1943:May). Item is in English.
  - Item 5: Political and Cultural Aspects of Jewish Post-War Problems., Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By Abraham G. Duker. Reprinted from The Jewish Social Service Quarterly, v.19:no.1 (1942:Sept.). Item is in English.
- Programs and Souvenirs., 1948-1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes 2 photographs.
- The Progressive, 1964; Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 1: The Progressive, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    By The Progressive. v.38:no.1 (1964:Jan.). Item is in English.